University Faculty; Records ua150
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Faculty Records1915-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Faculty
ua150
4.5 cubic ft.
The University Faculty consists of the voting faculty and is the body that grants power to the University Senate to develop and enact policy. The collection primarily consists of meeting minutes, audio recordings of meetings, and election results.
Biographical History
The earliest records of Faculty Meetings date from 1915. No by-laws define the nature or powers of the College Faculty before 1955. The 1955 SUNY Board of Trustees defined the college faculty as composed of the President of the State University, the executive dean and chief administrative officer of the college, and the academic staff. The responsibilities of the Faculty was to "participate in the development of the educational program of the college and... be responsible for the conduct of the college's instruction, research and service programs. [1] Subsequent SUNY Board pronouncements widened administrative representation on the College Faculty to administrative officers. [2] In 1967, the SUNY Board strengthened the role of the college and non-voting administrative officers and professional staff designated by the Faculty by-laws. [3] In 1968, the Chancellor of SUNY was added to the College Faculty. [4] In 1967 the SUNY Board strengthened the role of the College Faculty when it changed the wording of the responsibilities of the Faculty to state that the college faculty "shall have the obligation to participate significantly in the initiation, development and implementation of the educational program." [5]
From 1955 on, the SUNY Board of Trustees has designated the President of SUNY, the executive Dean or in their absence the chief administrative officer as the presiding officer of the College Faculty. [6] In 1967, the SUNY Trustees changed the designation of the presiding officer to indicate that the SUNY Chancellor or the chief administrative officer of the college would serve as the chairman of the Faculty, but provided that the selection of the presiding officer would be specified by the faculty by-laws. The same pronouncements by the SUNY Trustees gave either the chancellor or the chief administrative office the power to call faculty meetings and set agenda, and specified that either officer would be provided an opportunity to report to the faculty. [7]
The Faculty delegated its authority, granted by the SUNY Board of Trustees to "participate" in educational program development and its responsibility for "instruction, research, and service programs" to the Graduate Faculty, the Graduate Council, the Academic Council, Student Personnel Council, and the Faculty Council. [8] The Faculty retained the functions of ratifying actions of councils and committees, appointing committees to study specific problems, establishing requirements for degrees, establishing admissions standards, voting on the conferral of degrees, attendance and assistance at commencement, and election of officers to the SUNY Faculty Senate and the Faculty Council. [9] In 1966, the Faculty was responsible for creating the Faculty Senate out of the formerly disparate Councils of the University. [10] The new Faculty Senate was delegated all authority granted to the Faculty by the Board of Trustees, save the power to hold regular once a semester Faculty Meetings (formerly the faculty had met once a month during the academic year), to hold special meetings, and to establish a standing committee of the Faculty. The Nominations and Elections Committee which oversaw the nomination and election of Faculty Senators, determined the defintion of Faculty and Voting Faculty proposals for ammendments to the by-laws and referendum. [11] The Faculty has remained the ultimate source of Faculty and University Senate's authority. The subsequent Faculty By-Laws specifically empower the Senate to place items on the agenda of the Faculty Meeting, to call Faculty referenda, and issue an annual report of its activities to the Faculty. [12] The powers and responsibilities of the faculty have not undergone and substantial changes since 1969.
Notes 1. Policies of the Board of Trustees, SUNY, 1955, pp. 12-13. 2. Policies of the Board of Trustees, SUNY, 1959, p. 12. 3. Policies of the Board of Trustees, SUNY, 1966, p. 14. 4. Policies of the Board of Trustees, SUNY, 1967, p. 19. 5. Ibid., p. 15. 6. Policies of the Board of Trustees, SUNY, 1955, p. 13. 7. Policies of the Board of Trustees, SUNY 1967, p. 14-15. 8. Faculty Handbook, 1962, p. 21. 9. Faculty Handbook, 1962, p. 21. 10. Faculty Handbook, 1966-67, p. 7.1, section 3.2. 11. Ibid., p. 7.2-7.3, sections 5-6. 12. Faculty Handbook, 1968-69, p. 11, section 1.2, 1.5, 1.6.
Scope and Contents
The University Faculty consists of the voting faculty and is the body that grants power to the University Senate to develop and enact policy. On some overarching policy matters (such as amendments to the by-laws), decisions are voted on by the University Faculty.
Since the University Faculty has delegated most of its powers, the records it has created are not extensive. All that were created are minutes (and agendas for the later years). The minutes of the meetings contain synopses of reports presented by councils and committees of the University Senate and by the President of the University. Minutes from 1915 to 1937 are bound with the Minutes of the Faculty Council (200/01/01), which are a part of the records of the University Senate. Also included in the University Faculty records are the records of the Committee on Nominations and Elections. This committee is responsible for the elections of the senators to the University Senate.
Note: Minutes, 1915-1937 are interfiled with University Senate Minutes (200/01/01)
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged chronologically.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives, University Libraries, University at Albany, by the University Faculty.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
State University of New York -- Faculty; elections; Minutes (administrative records); Audiocassettes; State University of New York. University Faculty Senate
- University Faculty, Records, 1949-1991; 1
  - Minutes, 1949-1952 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1953-1956 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1957-1961 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1962-1969 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1971-1974 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1975-1980 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1981-1988 (Box 1 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 8)
  - Audio Cassette of Faculty Meeting, 1986 September 9 (Box 2 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 1)
  - Audio Cassette of Faculty Meeting, 1987 September 16 (Box 2 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 2)
  - Audio Cassette of Faculty Meeting, 1988 May 6 (Box 2 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 3)
  - Audio Cassette of Faculty Meeting, 1989 May 10 (Box 2 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 4)
  - Audio Cassette of Faculty Meeting, 1989 September 14 (Box 2 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 5)
  - Audio Cassette of Faculty Meeting, 1990 May 9 (Box 2 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 6)
  - Audio Cassette of Faculty Meeting (2 tapes), 1991 May 08 (Box 2 (1-University Faculty, Records), Folder 7)
- Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1966-1999; 2
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 1)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 2)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 3)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1972-1976 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 4)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1976-1979 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 5)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1979-1981 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 6)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 7)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 8)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1984-1985 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 9)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 10)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1986-1987 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 11)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 12)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1988-1991 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 13)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 14)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 15)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 16)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 17)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 18)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 19)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 20)
  - Committee on Nominations and Elections, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 21)
  - Senate Elections, 1966-67 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 1)
  - Senate Elections, 1967-68 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 2)
  - Senate Elections, 1968-69 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 3)
  - Senate Elections, 1969-70 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 4)
  - Senate Elections, 1970-71 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 5)
  - Senate Elections, 1971-72 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 6)
  - Senate Elections, 1972-73 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 7)
  - Senate Elections, 1973-74 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 8)
  - Senate Elections, 1974-75 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 9)
  - Senate Elections, 1975-76 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 10)
  - Senate Elections, 1976-77 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 11)
  - Senate Elections, 1977-1978 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 12)
  - Senate Elections, 1978-1979 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 13)
  - Senate Elections, 1979-1980 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 14)
  - Senate Elections, 1980-1981 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 15)
  - Senate Elections, 1981-1982 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 16)
  - Senate Elections, 1982-1983 (Box 2 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 17)
  - Senate Elections, 1983-1984 (Box 3 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 1)
  - Senate Elections, 1984-1985 (Box 4 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 2)
  - Senate Elections, 1985-1986 (Box 5 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 3)
  - Senate Elections, 1986-1987 (Box 6 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 4)
  - Senate Elections, 1987-1988 (Box 7 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 5)
  - Senate Elections, 1988-1989 (Box 8 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 6)
  - Senate Elections, 1989-1990 (Box 9 (2-Committee on Nominations and Elections), Folder 7)